I
私
Did I really hurt you?
本当にあなたを痛めてしまった
What?
どう
Can't I read?
私は見られない
What I mean is
私の意味は
Reading documents
公文書を見る
Should be done where documents are read
公文を見るべき場所で見るべきです
You raised this orchid?
このランはあなたが育てたのですか
This flower was raised by Yu'er
この花は玉児が育てたものです
Said to be the king among all flowers
曰く香りの国で最も王にふさわしいと
Wants to wait until it blooms before giving it to you
花が咲いてからあなたにあげます
Daughters are good
やっぱり娘の方がいいね
Daughters are thoughtful
娘は心が温かいね
Many rare seeds have arrived from the south
南から珍しい種がたくさん運ばれてきた
Have Yu'er
あなたは玉児に頼む
Pick what she likes
お気に入りを選んで
Father
父上
Dug canals all his life
一生川を掘り続けた
Truly wasted people and resources
民を疲弊させ財を損なうことは本当だ
Now the canals are open
今川が通れるようになった
Transporting military supplies back and forth
軍需物資の往復輸送
Is greatly convenient
とても便利になりました
You say, what a coincidence in the world
君世の中にこんな偶然があるって言うのか
I sometimes wonder
私は時々考え込むことがある
Father digging canals
父上が川を掘る
Might not just be for lychees and jade powder
それはライチとタル粉だけのせいではないのではないか
No matter what Father thought
父上がどう考えていようと
When Your Majesty goes north in the future
将来陛下が北伐するのを待つ
If it can be of great use, that's good
役に立てるならそれでいい
Your Majesty
陛下
Lady Chen requests an audience
陳夫人が面会を求める
How does she know I'm here?
彼女はどうして私がここにいると知っているの
You told her
あなたが彼女に言った
This
これ
The lady sent someone to ask this servant
その奥様は人を使って下僕に尋ねさせた
This servant dared not refuse to answer
召使いも答えないわけにはいかないよ
Let her in
彼女を入れてください
Yes
はい
Greetings, Lady Chen
陳夫人にお会いしたことがあります
Your Majesty
陛下
I heard a mad horse startled Your Majesty
私は聞きました狂馬が聖なる馬車を驚かせたと
Was very worried
非常に心配しています
Seeing Your Majesty safe here with my sister
陛下が妹のもとでお元気でいらっしゃることをお見かけしました
I am relieved
安心しました